There are lots of good reasons
to try and follow a healthier diet—
you lose weight,
you feel good,
but the main reason?
To live a longer, happier,
more productive life.
Welcome to the
NutritionFacts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we look at how to make
sense of the disparate results
from the four primate studies
on caloric restriction and lifespan.
Calorie restriction
in primates to extend lifespan.
Will it work?
There's only one way
to find out.
There have been
four investigations
of calorie restriction and
lifespan in nonhuman primates.
The first was published in 2003,
an analysis of the mortality
of 117 rhesus monkeys
followed for about 25 years
in a lab,
eight of whom had their
Purina monkey chow restricted.
The average survival
of the restricted monkeys
was to 32 years of age,
compared to 25 years
for the control monkeys.
However, it was more of
an observational study,
since the monkeys weren't
randomly assigned,
and although in the abstract
they talk about
the survival advantage
and how the ad libitum monkeys,
the eat-all-you-want monkeys,
had more than twice
the risk of death,
they acknowledge
deeper in the paper
that the difference in death
did not reach
statistical significance,
meaning it may very well
have been a fluke.
That was all we had, though,
until results
started trickling in
from the famous pair of studies
that involved randomizing
about 200 rhesus monkeys
to caloric restriction
or more normal diets,
one out of the University
of Wisconsin-Madison
and another from the
National Institute of Aging.
The UW study reported a 30
percent caloric restriction
significantly delayed disease
and improved survival,
but the NIA study did not.
In the UW study,
caloric restriction
reduced the incidence
of age-related diseases
including cancer,
cardiovascular disease,
brain atrophy,
and muscle wasting,
preserving muscle mass,
demonstrating caloric
restriction can delay aging,
but in the NIA study,
the difference
in age-related diseases
did not achieve
statistical significance.
In the UW study,
the restricted monkeys lived
to an average of about 29 years
compared to the control monkeys,
who lived closer to the average
for monkeys in captivity
of about 26 years old.
In contrast, though one
of the restricted monkeys
in the NIA study became
the longevity record holder
for the species at age 43,
on average, the restricted group
didn't live any longer
than the control animals.
Why the disparate results
between the two studies?
In the NIA study that found no
significant lifespan difference,
the control group
was not fed ad libitum,
but rather had food
portioned out to prevent
excessive weight gain.
In contrast,
in the UW study,
the control monkeys could eat
as much as they wanted
throughout the day
so ended up weighing more
than the NIA control animals.
Of course caloric restriction
would improve
the health and survival
of overweight monkeys
just as weight loss
would be beneficial
for overweight people,
but the null results
in the NIA study suggest
that normal weight people
might not benefit
from restricting further.
The NIA monkeys were also fed
a healthier diet.
The diet in the UW study
where they saw significant
benefit to cutting down
was an ultra-processed
concoction of largely
milk protein, corn oil,
corn starch, and table sugar,
whereas the NIA diet actually
included unprocessed plant foods
such as corn,
soybeans, and wheat,
and so actually had
some phytonutrients.
About 29 percent of the UW diet
was straight sugar,
compared to 4 percent
in the NIA diet.
American adults get about
17 teaspoons of sugar a day,
which is about
13 percent of calories.
The contrasting findings suggest
that the worse your diet is,
the more important it is
to eat less of it.
The fourth study
was on grey mouse lemurs,
among the smallest of primates,
standing just three inches tall.
Those randomized to
a 30 percent caloric restriction
compared to an ad libitum
control group
lived a whopping
50 percent longer.
And not just average lifespan,
but maximal lifespan.
The maximum lifespan was boosted
by about 20 percent.
However,
the "calorie restricted" group
still weighed heavier
than their wild counterparts,
so again this may just be
an illustration
of the harms of obesity
and another indictment against
all-you-can-eat buffets.
Also, those in the calorie
restriction group experienced
an acceleration of age-related
loss of grey matter
throughout their brains,
though this did not appear
to translate into cognitive
or behavioral differences.
Pooling the three rhesus monkey
studies together,
there seemed to be
lower age-related mortality
but no significant difference
in average lifespans overall
between the caloric
restriction groups
and the control groups.
Given the time and expense,
there is little chance
we are going to see any more
long-term primate studies
on caloric restriction
for life extension.
So what can we draw
from the primate data to date?
If you're overweight
or living off junk food,
eating less is a good idea.
In our next story,
we discover how a slower metabolism
may actually be a good thing.
We’ve known for more than a
century that calorie restriction
can increase the lifespan of animals,
and the metabolic slowdown
may be the mechanism.
That could be why the tortoise
lives 10 times longer than the hare.
Rabbits can live 10 to 20 years,
whereas “Harriet,” a tortoise
evidently collected from the
Galapagos by none other than
Charles Darwin himself in
the 1830s lived until 2006.
Slow and steady may win the race.
One of the ways your body lowers
your resting metabolic rate
is by creating cleaner-burning,
more efficient mitochondria,
the power plants that fuel our cells.
It’s like your body passes its
own fuel-efficiency standards.
These new mitochondria create
the same energy with less oxygen
and produce less free radical “exhaust.”
After all, your body is
afraid famine is afoot;
and so, it is trying to conserve
as much energy as it can.
The largest caloric
restriction trial to date
indeed found both metabolic slowing
and a reduction in free radical-induced
oxidative stress, both of which
may slow the rate of aging.
The flame that burns twice
as bright burns half as long.
But whether this will result
in greater human longevity
is an unanswered question.
Caloric restriction is
often said to extend
the lifespan of “every species studied”.
But that isn’t even true of all
strains within a single species.
Some scientists don’t
think calorie restriction
will improve human longevity at all;
others suggest a 20 percent calorie
restriction starting at age 25
and sustained for 52 years could
add 5 years onto your life.
Either way, the reduced oxidative stress
would be expected to
improve our health span.
Members of the
Calorie Restriction Society,
self-styled CRONies (for Calorie-
Restricted Optimal Nutrition),
appear to be in excellent health,
but they’re a rather unique
self-selected bunch of individuals.
You don’t really know until
you put it to the test.
Enter the CALERIE study,
the Comprehensive
Assessment of Long-term
Effects of Reducing Intake of Energy,
the first clinical trial to test
the effects of caloric restriction.
Hundreds of non-obese men
and women were randomized
to two years of 25% calorie restriction.
They only ended up achieving half
that but lost about 18 pounds
and three inches off their waists,
wiping out more than half of
their visceral abdominal fat.
That translated into significant
improvements in cholesterol levels,
triglycerides, insulin
sensitivity, and blood pressures.
Eighty percent of those who
were overweight when they started
were normal weight by the end,
compared to a 27-percent increase
in those who became overweight
in the control group.
In the famous Minnesota Starvation
Study that used conscientious objectors
as guinea pigs during World War II,
the study subjects suffered both
physically and psychologically,
experiencing depression,
irritability, and loss of libido.
The subjects started out lean, though,
and had their calorie intake cut in half.
The CALERIE study ended up
being 4 times less restrictive,
only about 12 percent below
baseline calorie intake,
and enrolled normal weight individuals,
which in the U.S. these days means
overweight on average.
As such, the CALERIE subjects
experienced nothing
but positive quality-of-life benefits,
with significant improvements in
mood, general health,
sex drive, and sleep.
They only ended up eating
about 300 fewer calories
than they were eating at baseline.
So, they got all these benefits—
the physiological benefits,
the psychological benefits—
all from only cutting about
a snack-sized bag of chips worth
of calories from their daily diets.
What happened at the end
of the trial, though?
In the Minnesota Starvation Study
and calorie deprivation experiments
done on Army Rangers, as soon as
subjects were released from restriction
they tended to rapidly regain
the weight and sometimes even more.
The leaner they started out,
the more their bodies seemed to
drive them to overeat to pack
back on the extra body fat.
In contrast, after the
completion of the CALERIE study,
even though their
metabolism was slowed,
they retained about 50 percent of
the weight loss two years later.
They must have acquired new
eating attitudes and behaviors
that allowed them to
keep their weight down.
After extended calorie
restriction, for example,
cravings for sugary, fatty, and
junky foods may actually go down.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest book, “How Not to Age”
is out now,
which premiered at #2 on the
New York Times Best Sellers list.
Check it out at your
local public library.
Of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is itself a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.